[Music]
to make sense of this visual proof
we first need to see that the number n
squared which is typically represented
by a square array
can be decomposed into two triangular
arrays with bases differing by one
and these arrays can be morphed into
arrays of triangles
that fit together like this to form a
triangular tiling of an equilateral
triangle by equilateral triangles
so each square can be visualized this
way
starting with the square of a multiple
of 3 let's say 3k
we can consider the trapezoid tile in
the lower left
with bases 2k and k
three copies of this trapezoid tile can
be used to cover the entire triangle
in this way so that 3k squared
is three times the size of the trapezoid
but the trapezoid is a difference of two
triangular tilings so it contains two k
squared
minus k squared triangles next
start with a square of a number that is
one less than a multiple of three
say three k minus one again we consider
the trapezoid tile in the lower left
this time with bases two k minus one and
k minus one
using three copies of this tile this
time covers all but
one of the small triangles in the tiling
therefore
the quantity 3k minus 1 squared is equal
to 1
plus 3 times the quantity 2k minus 1
squared minus k minus 1 squared
as the trapezoid is again the difference
of two squares
finally if we start with a square of a
number one more than a multiple of three
say three k plus one then we can again
use three copies of a trapezoid tile
but this time the bases are two k plus
one
and k plus one and again these cover the
entire triangle
except for one middle triangle
therefore we conclude that three k plus
one squared
is one plus three times the quantity two
k plus one squared
minus k plus one squared as again the
trapezoid covers the difference of
squares
therefore we've seen that n squared is
congruent to 0 mod 3
if n is congruent to 0 mod 3 and n
squared is congruent to 1 mod 3
if n is not congruent to 0 mod 3. since
every number is either a multiple of 3
one more than a multiple of 3 or 1 less
than a multiple of 3
we've seen that every square is
congruent to 0 or 1 mod 3.
you